A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare Interests - General Files, Series P FA325
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Settlements
  - Settlements - Riverside Community House, 1937-1959 (Box 48, Folder 536)
    The House merged with the Goddard Neighborhood Center to become the Goddard-Riverside Community Center. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave a gift in 1941. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel.
    43R
  - Settlements - Riverside Community House, 1937-1959 (Box 48, Folder 0536A)
  - Settlements - Stryker's Lane Community Center, 1927-1950 (Box 48, Folder 537)
    This was a community center in the West 50s area, based on the self-helf idea. It included a branch Employment Agency. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributed. The center closed in 1950. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, Thomas B. Appleget, Arthur W. Packard.
    43S
  - Settlements - Saint James Community Center, 1945-1951 (Box 48, Folder 538)
    Appeals for aid in building a Harlem community center were declined. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard.
  - Settlements - Union Settlement, 1932-1947 (Box 48, Folder 539)
    This was organized by alumni of the Union Theological Seminary. John D. Rockefeller 3rd and Mary French Rockefeller contributed. Correspondents include Dana S. Creel, Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Mary French Rockefeller.
    43U
  - Settlements - Union Settlement, 1948-1961 (Box 49, Folder 540)
  - Settlements - Union Settlement, 1948-1961 (Box 49, Folder 0540A)
  - Settlements - United Neighborhood Houses, 1941-1962 (Box 49, Folder 541)
    Most appeals were declined. Warren T. Lindquist served on the board of directors. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel.
    43U1
  - Settlements - United Neighborhood Houses, 1941-1962 (Box 49, Folder 541A)
  - Settlements - Williamsburg Settlement, 1946-1956 (Box 49, Folder 542)
    43W
  - Settlements - Yorkville Music School, East Side House, 1924-1933 (Box 49, Folder 543)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave the school $10,000 from 1924 to 1933 but discontinued contributions for policy reasons. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, Thomas B. Appleget, Arthur W. Packard.
    43Y
  - Settlements and Science and Lecture Groups - Legal Size Material (Box 55, Folder 623)
    Folders 494-553.
  - Settlements - Henry Street Visiting Nurse Service - Pledge, November 4, 1932 (Box 57, Folder 637)
    Henry Street Settlement Campaign Funds, as of December 31, 1928.
    Removed from Box 45, Folder 513.
- Science and Lecture Groups
  - Science and Lecture Groups - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1908-1931 (Box 49, Folder 544)
    John D. Rockefeller gave $1,000 in 1908. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. declined a speaking invitation in 1919. All later requests were declined.
    177
  - Science and Lecture Groups - National Institute of Social Sciences, 1919-1961 (Box 49, Folder 545)
    177.2
  - Science and Lecture Groups - National Institute of Social Sciences - John D. Rockefeller 3rd, 1938-1961 (Box 49, Folder 546)
    John D. Rockefeller 3rd declined membership offers. Blanchette Hooker Rockefeller was a member, 1952-1957.
  - Science and Lecture Groups - National Institute of Social Sciences - Laurance S. Rockefeller, 1957-1961 (Box 49, Folder 547)
    Laurance S. Rockefeller was given the Gold Medal in 1959.
  - Science and Lecture Groups - National Institute of Social Sciences - Laurance S. Rockefeller, 1960 (Box 49, Folder 547A)
  - Science and Lecture Groups - American Institute for Social Service, 1899-1935 (Box 49, Folder 548)
    John D. Rockefeller gave three small gifts from 1899 to 1901, but later requests were declined.
    177.3
  - Science and Lecture Groups - Town Hall, 1921-1946 (Box 49, Folder 549)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $110,000 toward debts and the building program of Town Hall from 1922 to 1924 but declined later requests. Nelson A. Rockefeller declined invitations to appear on a program. Correspondents include Raymond B. Fosdick, Dana S. Creel, Nelson A. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    177.5
  - Science and Lecture Groups - Town Hall, 1921-1946 (Box 49, Folder 0549A)
    David Rockefeller contributed $100 in 1953. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
  - Science and Lecture Groups - Town Hall, 1947-1961 (Box 49, Folder 550)
  - Science and Lecture Groups - Town Hall, 1947-1961 (Box 49, Folder 0550A)
  - Science and Lecture Groups - Town Hall - Asia Series, 1954-1955 (Box 49, Folder 551)
  - Science and Lecture Groups - Museo Social, Buenos Aires, 1924-1925 (Box 49, Folder 552)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. paid the expenses of the United States delegate to the Social Science meeting in Buenos Aires. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, Beardsley Ruml, G. Sherwell.
    177.6
  - Science and Lecture Groups - Calvin Bullock Forum, 1945-1961 (Box 50, Folder 553)
    The Forum was a "Wall Street institution" holding lectures for financiers. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. declined to speak but John D. Rockefeller 3rd spoke on the Far East in 1947, 1948, 1952, and 1954. There are no copies of his addresses. Correspondents include Hugh Bullock, John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
  - Science and Lecture Groups - Academy of Political Science, 1910-1917 (Box 50, Folder 554)
    In the early day the Academy was particularly interested in "dissemination of sound economic thought." John D. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributed but declined most of the appeals and invitations. John D. Rockefeller 3rd and Laurance S. Rockefeller are Life Members. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Charles O. Heydt, Willard S. Richardson, Starr J. Murphy, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
    177.11
  - Science and Lecture Groups - Academy of Political Science, 1919-1959 (Box 50, Folder 555)
  - Science and Lecture Groups - Academy of Political Science, 1919-1959 (Box 50, Folder 0555A)
    In the early day the Academy was particularly interested in "dissemination of sound economic thought." John D. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributed but declined most of the appeals and invitations. David Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, and Laurance S. Rockefeller are Life Members. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Charles O. Heydt, Willard S. Richardson, Starr J. Murphy, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
  - Science and Lecture Groups - Academy of Political Science - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Correspondence, 1935-1961 (Box 50, Folder 556)
    Small contributions were made and dues were paid. John D. Rockefeller 3rd eventually became a Life Member. There is a marked copy of the 1948 Proceedings: "America's New Foreign Policy."
  - Science and Lecture Groups - New York Community Trust, 1918-1936 (Box 50, Folder 557)
    The Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial fund made a contribution. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Thomas B. Appleget, Arthur Woods.
    181
  - Science and Lecture Groups - New York Community Trust, 1937-1962 (Box 50, Folder 558)
  - Science and Lecture Groups - New York Community Trust, 1937-1962 (Box 50, Folder 0558A)
    David Rockefeller was a trustee.
  - Science and Lecture Groups - New York Community Trust - Westchester Welfare Foundation, 1926-1930 (Box 50, Folder 559)
  - Science and Lecture Groups - Proposed National Foundation (National Community Trust), 1929-1930 (Box 50, Folder 560)
    There were plans for a national trust to distribute funds for worthy causes, from charity to preservation of historic sites. The plans grew out of the New York Community Trust. The plans fell through and the proposed Rockefeller contribution was never made.
    181.2
  - Science and Lecture Groups - American Academy of Political and Social Science, 1899-1958 (Box 50, Folder 561)
    177.1
  - Science and Lecture Groups - American Academy of Political and Social Science, 1899-1958 (Box 50, Folder 0561A)
- United Service Organization (USO)
  - United Service Organization - General, 1941-1942 (Box 50, Folder 562)
    Here is detailed information about organizing the USO and its initial fundraising program. Laurance S. Rockefeller gave a speech in Tarrytown and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave an address containing his Credo. There were complaints about USO operations but the program was a general success. The USO was reactivated in 1951 but Rockefeller support declined after 1957. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel, Laurance S. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Chester Barnard, Lindsay Kimball.
    236
  - United Service Organization - General, 1942-1945 (Box 50, Folder 563)
  - United Service Organization - General, 1946-1961 (Box 50, Folder 564)
  - United Service Organization - General, 1959 (Box 50, Folder 0564A)
  - United Service Organization - Agreement with Agencies, 1941-1942 (Box 51, Folder 565)
    Samples of contract used by USO.
  - United Service Organization - American Social Hygiene Funds, 1941 (Box 51, Folder 566)
    USO gave ASHA funds to study vice conditions.
  - United Service Organization - By-Laws and Certificate of Incorporation, 1941-1947 (Box 51, Folder 567)
    Originals with the amendments.
  - United Service Organization - Sponsoring Committee, 1941 (Box 51, Folder 568)
    There are details about the formation of the committee with John D. Rockefeller, Jr. as chairman.
  - United Service Organization - John D. Rockefeller 3rd Correspondence, 1941-1961 (Box 51, Folder 569)
    Appeals for service were usually declined.
  - United Service Organization - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondence
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. held various posts and aided in recruiting high-level personnel and financial arrangements. There are enigmatic references to the USO's problems and a long memo about USO sectarianism. Kimball appraised and reported on how a future USO-type agency should be operated. There was planning for a post-war USO and liquidation and reactivation. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. continued to help in an unofficial capacity and expressed disapproval of rapid demobilization and a naive attitude about post-war "peace." Correspondents include Lindsay Kimball, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, Thomas E. Dewey, Winthrop Aldrich, Harper Sibley, General F. Osborn, Walter Hoving, Chester Barnard, W. Spencer Robertson.
    236A
    - United Service Organization - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondence, 1941-1942 (Box 51, Folder 570)
    - United Service Organization - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondence, 1941-1942 (Box 51, Folder 0570A)
    - United Service Organization - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondence, 1942 (Box 51, Folder 571)
    - United Service Organization - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondence, 1942-1943 (Box 51, Folder 572)
    - United Service Organization - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondence, 1944-1947 (Box 51, Folder 573)
    - United Service Organization - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondence, 1947-1960 (Box 51, Folder 574)
  - United Service Organization - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondence - Mr. Barnard, 1942-1950 (Box 51, Folder 575)
    Mr. Barnard was selected to head the USO. There is a long 1944 memo evaluating USO work. His resignation, recommendations for a successor, and farewell procedures and honors are documented.
  - United Service Organization - Family Contributions, 1941-1946 (Box 52, Folder 576)
    Details of campaigns and family contributions. Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller, David Rockefeller, Winthrop Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
    236.1
  - United Service Organization - Family Contributions, 1941-1946 (Box 52, Folder 0576A)
  - United Service Organization - Family Contributions, 1946-1955 (Box 52, Folder 577)
  - United Service Organization - Family Contributions, 1956-1961 (Box 52, Folder 578)
  - United Service Organization - Contributions and Appeals (A-M), 1941-1946 (Box 52, Folder 579)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. wrote letters of appeal and received responses. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., L. F. Kimball.
  - United Service Organization - Contributions and Appeals (N-Z), 1941-1946 (Box 52, Folder 580)
  - United Service Organization - Contributions and Appeals - Miscellaneous, 1941-1957 (Box 52, Folder 581)
  - United Service Organization - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Address, July 8, 1941, 1941-1945 (Box 52, Folder 582)
    This address included John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s "Credo." There were requests for the right to print his Credo and a response to the radio address on behalf of the USO. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    236.2
  - United Service Organization - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Address, July 8, 1941, 1946-1951 (Box 52, Folder 583)
  - United Service Organization - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Address, July 8, 1941, 1952-1961 (Box 52, Folder 584)
  - United Service Organization - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Address, July 8, 1941 - Address Over Radio, 1941-1964 (Box 53, Folder 585)
    The July 8 address was given over CBS.
  - United Service Organization - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Address, July 8, 1941 - Publication in "Readers Digest", 1944-1945 (Box 53, Folder 586)
    The Credo was published in the January, 1945 issue but the order of the points was changed.
  - United Service Organization - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Address, July 8, 1941 - Printing Card (Box 53, Folder 587)
    Publication of the Credo by T. J. Ross.
  - United Service Organization - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Address, July 8, 1941 - Clippings (Box 53, Folder 588)
    There was newspaper coverage of the speech and the Credo itself.
  - United Service Organization - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Address, July 8, 1941 - Letters of Appreciation (A-C), 1941-1943 (Box 53, Folder 589)
  - United Service Organization - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Address, July 8, 1941 - Letters of Appreciation (D-J), 1941-1942 (Box 53, Folder 590)
  - United Service Organization - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Address, July 8, 1941 - Letters of Appreciation (K-R), 1941-1942 (Box 53, Folder 591)
  - United Service Organization - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Address, July 8, 1941 - Letters of Appreciation (S-Y) (Box 53, Folder 592)
  - United Service Organization - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Addresses - General, 1942 (Box 53, Folder 593)
    236.21
  - United Service Organization - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Addresses - June 3, 1941, 1941-1942 (Box 53, Folder 594)
  - United Service Organization - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Addresses - May 11, 1942 (Box 53, Folder 595)
  - United Service Organization - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Addresses - Luncheon, February 4, 1943 (Box 53, Folder 596)
  - United Service Organization - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Addresses - September 16, 1943 (Box 53, Folder 597)
  - United Service Organization - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Addresses - December 11, 1945, 1945-1946 (Box 53, Folder 598)
    This was the fourth annual luncheon.
  - United Service Organization - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Addresses - October 10, 1946, 1946-1959 (Box 53, Folder 599)
    This was given for the Cleveland Community Trust.
  - United Service Organization - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Addresses - October 24, 1947 (Box 53, Folder 600)
  - United Service Organization - 1942 Campaign (Box 53, Folder 601)
    Here are details about securing a campaign chairman and an advisory council, and the success of the campaign. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    236.3
  - United Service Organization - 1942 Campaign (Box 53, Folder 0601A)
  - United Service Organization - Dinners Given by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and USO, 1941-1949 (Box 54, Folder 602)
    236.4
  - United Service Organization - Dinners Given by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and USO - June 19, 1941 (Box 54, Folder 603)
  - United Service Organization - Dinners Given by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and USO - Shell Union Oil Corporation, 1941-1942 (Box 54, Folder 604)
  - United Service Organization - Dinners Given by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and USO - March 19, 1942 (Box 54, Folder 605)
  - United Service Organization - Dinners Given by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and USO - April 28, 1944 (Box 54, Folder 606)
    This dinner was given at the Rainbow Room.
  - United Service Organization - Dinners Given by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and USO - January 31, 1946 (Box 54, Folder 607)
    This was a luncheon at the Rainbow Lounge.
  - United Service Organization - Dinners Given by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and USO - June 20, 1946 (Box 54, Folder 608)
  - United Service Organization - Dinners Given by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and USO - February 1949 (Box 54, Folder 609)
  - United Service Organization - Minnesota Tribute Dinner for John D. Rockefeller, Jr., 1944 (Box 54, Folder 610)
    Newspaper clippings, mostly from the Midwest, about the dinner.
  - United Service Organization - Overseas, 1942-1944 (Box 54, Folder 611)
    Details of agreements with the Army and Navy on USO overseas work and legal questions. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    236.5
  - United Service Organization - John D. Rockefeller, Jr.-Arthur W. Packard Correspondence, 1919-1947 (Box 54, Folder 612)
    There were plans for USO work. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    236.6
  - United Service Organization - Dr. Kimball's Survey, 1942 (Box 54, Folder 613)
    Arrangements were made for securing L. F. Kimball to make a survey of the USO. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., L. F. Kimball, Arthur W. Packard, Harper Sibley.
    236.7A
  - United Service Organization - Dr. Kimball's Survey - Study and Investigation, 1942-1943 (Box 54, Folder 614)
    There was an initial proposal of a National Welfare Committee to the office of the Coordinator of Health and Education, etc. Information on the formation of the USO, Raymond B. Fosdick's tour of camps, and the investigation of pre-USO conditions. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Raymond B. Fosdick, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., L. F. Kimball.
    236.7C
  - United Service Organization - Printed Material - Press Releases, 1941-1948 (Box 54, Folder 615)
    Newsletters, fact sheets, directories, releases, and reports.
    236.8
  - United Service Organization - Printed Material - Clippings, 1941-1958 (Box 54, Folder 616)
  - United Service Organization - Legal Size Material (Box 55, Folder 624)
    Folders 564-615.